A Guide to the National Committee on United States-China Relations records, RG 7, Accession 7 FA1189
Rockefeller Archive Center
National Committee on United States-China Relations records, RG 7, Accession 7
1957-2014
Rockefeller Archive Center
National Committee on United States-China Relations, Inc.
FA1189
22.77 Cubic Feet 58 document boxes, 1 oversized document box
Conditions Governing Access
Open for research with select materials restricted as noted. Brittle or damaged items are available at the discretion of RAC. Researchers interested in accessing digital media (floppy disks, CDs, DVDs, etc.) in this collection must use an access surrogate. The original items may not be accessed because of preservation concerns. To request an access surrogate be made, or if you are unsure if there is an access surrogate, please contact an archivist. When requesting audiovisual material, please refer to the Title and the AV Number (example: AV 1916). Researchers are asked to check the "Restrictions" note for each Title. If a Title does not currently have an access copy, please contact an RAC archivist for further instruction.
Biographical / Historical
The National Committee on United States – China Relations (NCUSCR) was established in 1966 as a nonprofit educational organization with a mission to encourage mutual understanding and dialogue between citizens of the United States and China. The National Committee came into being through the cooperative efforts of scholars and civic, religious, and business leaders who, at a time of mutual hostility between the two countries, sought to stimulate public discussion about China and the United States' relations with it by sponsoring conferences, seminars, publications, and other education and outreach programs. In 1972, the National Committee sponsored the Chinese table tennis team's historic U. S. visit. This round of "Ping Pong Diplomacy," which followed closely on Richard Nixon's visit to China in February 1972, helped pave the way for later exchanges and, eventually, for the normalization of relations with China in 1979. Building on these cultural exchanges, the National Committee came to be a primary organizer of professional and policy exchanges between the two countries (and including Hong Kong and Taiwan), in the areas of foreign affairs and international relations, economic development, governance and legal affairs, education, mass media, environmental and global issues, etc. As its role in exchanges became more prominent, the National Committee turned over some of its educational programs to the Asia Society in the late 1970s, but it continues its educational role through public education events and ongoing outreach. Funding for the National Committee comes from the United States government (especially the Department of State), corporations, and foundations, as well as from its individual membership.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
The National Committee on United States-China Relations donated its records to the Rockefeller Archive Center by deed of gift dated March 27, 2015.
Arrangement
The records of the National Committee on United States – China Relations are divided into ten record groups, which reflect the order in which the records were received (but which are otherwise an artificial distinction). The records are sorted intellectually into series, which carry over through all record groups, but they have received minimal physical rearrangement. RG 7 of the NCUSCR records is arranged into fourteen series: 1 – Events; 2 – Exchanges - General; 3 – Exchanges to China; 4 – Exchanges from China; 5 – Conferences, Seminars, Workshops, and Dialogues; 6 – Publications and Reports; 8 – Programs, Projects, and Proposals; 9 – Ping Pong Diplomacy; 10 – Development; 11 – Board of Directors, Committees, and Members records; 12 – HIV-AIDS; 13 – ACS/ACF Programs and Staff; 15 – Clippings and Reference; and 16 – Sister Cities.
Scope and Contents
RG 7 notably includes the records of the America – China Society, from its founding in 1987 through its merger with the National Committee in 2001. Board records in RG 7 document Board and Executive Committee meetings from around 2002/2004 to 2014. Significant subjects in RG 7 include the Shenyang Acrobats' U. S. tour, 1971 – 1972, and National Committee efforts (two-way exchanges and workshops) on behalf of HIV-AIDS awareness and prevention in China. Finally, RG 7 contains information on exchange trips and conferences sponsored by other, "outside" organizations, such as the Committee on Scholarly Communication with the People's Republic of China, whose activities sometimes paralleled the National Committee's own programs.It also includes materials on Sister City programs with China.
- Events, 1977, 1988, 2003; 1
  - United States and China: An Overview, 1977 February 21 (Box 19, Folder 189)
    Scope and Contents
    Panel discussion cosponsored by the Institute of World Affairs, University of Wisconsin - Milwaukee, and NCUSCR.
  - Briefings on U. S. Presidential Elections for Chinese Mission to the U. N. and Consular Officials, 1988 (Box 19, Folder 190)
    Briefings by Michael Pilsipher and Lou Harris.
  - Long Yongtu Visit (Seattle, Los Angeles, and Washington, DC), 2003 June 9-19 (Box 19, Folder 191)
    The University of Washington and the NCUSCR cosponsored Long's visit. Head of the Boao Forum on Asia, Long participated in a series of public programs and briefings on China's economic reforms and role in Asia.
- Exchanges - General, 1969-2011; 2
  The General Exchanges series in RG 7 contains trip reports and other records, mainly for the 1970s – 1980s, relating to various "outside" exchanges with China, which were undertaken without the direct support and sponsorship of the National Committee. Other significant materials include correspondence with the Committee on Scholarly Communication with the People's Republic of China, 1969-1987, including files on CSCPRC delegations from China, and general assessments of exchange programs.
  - Outside Exchanges - Trip Reports (General), 1976-1988 (Box 4, Folder 46)
    Delegation of Congresswomen to the PRC, 1975 December 30 - 1976 January 9. Congressional Foreign Policy study mission to China, 1976 April 17-23. Harlan Cleveland, China Diary, 1976. Wang Jo-shui, "Wondering about America," 1979 February. Andre Schriffin, "The New China - No Turning Back," The Nation, 1988 February 6.
  - Outside Exchanges - Trip Reports (Education), 1978 (Box 4, Folder 47)
    Clark Kerr, Observations on the Relations Between Education and Work in the People's Republic of China: Report of a Study Group, 1978. Adult Education Association China Tour, 1978 September.
  - Outside Exchanges - Librarians Delegation from the People's Republic of China, 1973 September 28 - November 3 (Box 4, Folder 48)
    Trip coordinated by Committee on Scholarly Communication with the People's Republic of China.
  - Outside Exchanges - Education in China Today, 1974 (Box 4, Folder 49)
    Mountain View Center for Environmental Education, Outlook (Special Issue, 1975). Report on visit to April 1974 visit to China, by Elizabeth T. Kellogg.
  - Outside Exchanges - American Insect Control Delegation Trip Report, 1975 August 3-28 (Box 4, Folder 50)
    Visit organized by the Committee on Scholarly Communication with the People's Republic of China. CSCPRC Report no. 2, Insect Control in the People's Republic of China (1977).
  - Outside Exchanges - American Solid State Physics Delegation Trip Report, 1975 September (Box 4, Folder 51)
    Visit organized by the Committee on Scholarly Communication with China. CSCPRC Report no. 1, Solid State Physics in the People's Republic of China (1976).
  - Outside Exchanges - Huhsien Peasant Paintings Exhibition, 1973-1974, 1977 (Box 5, Folder 52)
  - Outside Exchanges - National Council of Teachers of Mathematics Delegation (Jerry P. Becker), 1973-1975, 1977-1978 (Box 5, Folder 53)
  - Outside Exchanges - China Study Group on Environmental Issues, 1975-1978 (Box 5, Folder 54)
    Women's group of architects, urban planners, and preservationists. Study tour to China in (1977) hosted by the Architecture Society of China. A delegation of Chinese architects visited the U. S. in November 1978.
  - Outside Exchanges - Amateur Basketball Association of the United States of America, 1973-1978 (Box 5, Folder 55)
    Includes two black and white 8x10 prints of the Select Women's Basketball Team on 1978 tour to China.
  - Outside Exchanges - University of California Berkeley and San Francisco Museum of Modern Art Trip to China, 1979 May (Box 5, Folder 56)
    Earl F. Cheit and June A. Cheit, A Glimpse at Some Flowers from the Bus: 17 Days in China following Normalization (1980).
  - Outside Exchanges - Shanghai Acrobatic Theater, 1980 (Box 5, Folder 57)
  - Outside Exchanges - American Association of State Colleges and Universities, 1981 (Box 5, Folder 58)
    Hosted Local Higher Education Delegation from China, October 21 - November 14, 1981.
  - Outside Exchanges - Case Study of the Personnel Exchange Program Between Hangzhou University and Indiana University, circa 1984 (Box 5, Folder 59)
    Report by Li Kexing.
  - Outside Exchanges - Jurists from China (People's Court Delegation), 1985 May 3-19 (Box 5, Folder 60)
    Visit arranged by Medidian House International, on behalf of the United States Information Agency.
  - Outside Exchanges - International Republican Institute, 1994 (Box 5, Folder 61)
    Two reports: People's Republic of China - Election Observation Report, 1994 May 15-31 (Fujian Province). Hong Kong - Rule of Law Mission Report, 1994 June 12-19.
  - Outside Exchanges - National Committee on American Foreign Policy, 1996, 2002 (Box 5, Folder 62)
    Developing a Peaceful, Stable, and Cooperative Relationship with China (study group visit to China and Taiwan, 1996 June 9-23). Summary of the NCAFP Trip to Beijing, Shanghai, and Taipei, 2002 April 25 - May 5.
  - Outside Exchanges - United States Army Band ("Pershing's Own") and the Military Band of the People's Liberation Army of China, 2011 May (Box 5, Folder 63)
    Program brochure for Friendship and Cooperation through Music
  - Strength Through Wisdom: A Critique of U. S. Capability, 1979 November (Box 6, Folder 73)
    Report to the President from the President's Commission on Foreign Language and International Studies.
  - Directory of Resources for International Cultural and Educational Exchanges, 1987 (Box 6, Folder 74)
    United States Information Agency.
  - Directory of British Organizations with a China Interest, 1999 (Box 6, Folder 75)
    Fourth edition. File also includes Annual Report of the Great Britain - China Centre, 1998/1999.
  - Access Asia: A Guide to Specialists and Current Research, 1993; Published Material (Box 6, Folder 76)
  - Committee on Scholarly Communication with the People's Republic of China, 1969-1974 (Box 8, Folder 95-96)
  - Committee on Scholarly Communication with the People's Republic of China, 1975 - 1987 (Box 9, Folder 97-102)
    Correspondence and reports concerning exchange programs and delegations.
  - Committee on Scholarly Communication with the People's Republic of China (Delegations from China), 1972 (Box 9, Folder 103)
    Lists, itineraries, and reports.
  - Committee on Scholarly Communication with the People's Republic of China (Delegations from China), 1973-1974 (Box 10, Folder 104)
  - Committee on Scholarly Communication with the People's Republic of China (Newsletter), 1976, 1979, 2003 (Box 10, Folder 105)
  - Scholarly Exchange with the People's Republic of China, 1971-1973 (Box 10, Folder 106)
    File consists of an unidentified paper on Scholarly Exchange with the P.R.C., 1971-1972, and an article on the May 27, 1973, exchange agreements between the Committee on Scholarly Communication with the P.R.C. and the Scientific and Technical Assocation of the P. R. C.
  - U. S. - P. R. C. Scientific Cooperation: An Assessment of the First Two Years (Richard P. Suttmeier), 1981 June (Box 10, Folder 107)
    Study conducted for the U. S. Department of State.
  - Research Opportunities in China for American Humanists and Social Scientists: Report, 1982 (Box 10, Folder 108)
    Draft report of the Humanities and Social Science Planning Commission, of the Committee for Scholarly Communication with the P. R. C. The report was presented at the University Meeting on Educational Exchanges with China, February 19, 1982.
- Exchanges to China, 1977-1981; 3
  - United States Tennis Delegation, 1977 October 11-26 (Box 19, Folder 192)
    Planning, Itinerary, and Follow-Up.
  - United States Tennis Delegation, 1977 October 11-26 (Box 20, Folder 193)
    Namelists and Bios.
  - United States Tennis Delegation, 1977 October 11-26; Still Images: 12 black-and-white and 1 color print, mainly 5"x 7" - 8"x10". (Box 20, Folder 193)
    Images include publicity photos of delegates.
  - Ice Sport - Figure Skating Delegation (Cancelled), 1980 November (Box 20, Folder 194)
    Background and planning for proposed delegation.
  - Public Television (PBS) Study Group - General, 1981 February 21 - March 11 (Box 20, Folder 195)
    Namelist, Background and Planning
  - Public Television (PBS) Study Group - itinerary and Follow-Up, 1981 February 21 - March 11 (Box 20, Folder 196)
  - Public Television (PBS) Study Group - Report, 1981 February 21 - March 11 (Box 20, Folder 197)
    Tom Skinner, Some Notes on a Trip to China.
  - Arts Administrators Study Group, 1981 June 16 - July 10 (Box 20, Folder 198)
- Exchanges from China, 1972-2011; 4
  - Shenyang Acrobats: Background and Planning, 1972 December 16 - 1973 January 13; Still Image: Individual headshots mounted on sheets of paper. A couple of photos are missing. (Box 7, Folder 78-79)
    Includes schedule, rosters, photographic list of troupe members, guidelines, and press announcement.
  - Shenyang Acrobats: Itineraries, 1972 December 16 - 1973 January 13 (Box 7, Folder 80)
  - Shenyang Acrobats: Canada, 1972 November-December (Box 7, Folder 81)
    The acrobatic troupe toured in Canada prior to their U.S. visit.
  - Shenyang Acrobats: Chicago, 1972 December 16 - 25 (Box 7, Folder 82)
  - Shenyang Acrobats: Indianapolis, 1972 December 25 - 31 (Box 7, Folder 83)
  - Shenyang Acrobats: New York, 1972 December 31 - 1973 January 7 (Box 7, Folder 84)
  - Shenyang Acrobats: Washington, DC, 1973 January 7 - 13 (Box 7, Folder 85-86)
    Washington visit hosted by Meridian House International and its International Visitors Service Council.
  - Shenyang Acrobats: Travel Arrangements, 1972 December 16 - 1973 January 13 (Box 8, Folder 87)
    Menus, rooming, and flight arrangements.
  - Shenyang Acrobats: Program Booklet, 1972 December 16 - 1973 January 13 (Box 8, Folder 88)
  - Shenyang Acrobats: Press, 1972 December 16 - 1973 January 13 (Box 8, Folder 89)
    Includes Chinese Press reactions.
  - Shenyang Acrobats: Television and Film Documentaries, 1973, 1980 (Box 8, Folder 90)
  - Shenyang Acrobats: Commemorative Portfolio, 1973-1975 (Box 8, Folder 91)
    Correspondence with Laura Volkerding concerning preparation of photographic portfolios from the Troupe's Chicago stay. There are no photographs in the file.
  - Shenyang Acrobats: Thank Yous, 1972 December 16 - 1973 January 13 (Box 8, Folder 92)
  - Shenyang Acrobats: Follow-Up, 1973-1975, 2003, 2006 (Box 8, Folder 93)
  - Shenyang Acrobats: Brochures and Publications, 1999-2011 (Box 8, Folder 94)
- Conferences, Seminars, Workshops, and Dialogues, 1968-2013; 5
  - Outside Conferences - General, 1968, 1977, 1991-1997, 2004 (Box 5, Folder 64-65)
    University of Chicago Center for Policy Study, China Briefing, 1968. Proceedings, Wisconsin Conference on China, 1977 May 13-14. U. S. - Japan Policy Dialogue on China: Economic Issues, 1991. 85th and 89th American Assemblies, 1994, 1996. Panel on Sino-U. S. Relations, Institute for International Studies of Beijing Academy of Social Sciences and Center for American Studies, Beijing Society for Comparative International Studies, Trends of Future Sino-US Relations and Policy Proposals, 1995. U. S. Policy toward China, University of Georgia Russell Symposium, 1997; announcement of E-governance Conference, Beijing, 2004.
  - Outside Conferences - World Trade Conference (Chicago), 1974 February 27-28 (Box 5, Folder 66)
    Conference sponsored by the Chicago Associaiton of Commerce and Industry and the International Trade Club of Chicago. Charles Yost moderated panel on Developing Trade with the PRC.
  - Outside Conferences - New Ideas and Concepts in Sino-American Relations, 1992 November 18-20 (Box 5, Folder 67)
    Report and proceedings. Conference sponsored by the American Enterprise Institute and the Shanghai Institute for International Studies.
  - Outside Conferences - China's Future: Implications for US Interests, 1999 September 24 (Box 6, Folder 68)
    Conference Report. Sponsored by National Intelligence Council and the Library of Congress.
  - Outside Conferences - National Committee on American Foreign Policy, 1998-2000, 2009-2011 (Box 6, Folder 69-70)
    Roundtables on U. S. - China Policy and Cross-Strait Relations, 1998-2000. Making Peace in the Taiwan Strait, 2009 May. Sweet and Sour: Candid Talks to Improve U. S. - China Relations and U. S. - China Strategic Dialogue Report, 2010 November - 2011 April.
  - Outside Conferences - US - China Economic Relations in the Next Ten Years: Towards Deeper Engagement and Mutual Benefit, 2013 (Box 6, Folder 71)
    Study sponsored by the China - United States Exchange Foundation. Forward, Executive Summary, Part 1, and Part 2 (Contents). On USB card: Part 2 (Reports), US - China 2022.
  - Outside Conferences - US - China Economic Relations in the Next Ten Years: Towards Deeper Engagement and Mutual Benefit, 2013; USB card (4 GB), attached to hard plastic "business card." (Box 6, Folder 71)
    Part 2 (Reports), US - China 2022.
    Conditions Governing Access
    Access copy currently unavailable. Researchers interested in accessing digital media in this collection must use an access surrogate. The original items may not be accessed because of preservation concerns. Please contact an archivist if you are uncertain if there is an access surrogate or to ask that one be made.
  - China - United States Sustained Dialogue, 1986-2001 (Box 6, Folder 72)
    Volume published by the Kettering Foundation.
  - Central - Local Fiscal Relations in China Conference, 2006 July 10-11 (Box 15, Folder 149)
    Renmin University, Beijing. Also titled, Central - Provincial Fiscal Relations.
  - Central - Local Fiscal Relations in China Conference, 2006 July 10-11; Still Image: Two 4"x 6" color prints, and two 5"x 7" color prints. (Box 15, Folder 149)
    Photos consist of two snapshots of conference and one group photo (with duplicate print).
- Publications and Reports, 1967-1971; 6
  - China Clearinghouse, 1967 August 1 - 1969 (Box 15, Folder 150)
    File contains set of China Clearinghouse newsletter.
  - Resources on China, 1967-1971 (Box 15, Folder 151)
    Includes Annotated Guide to Modern China, 1967 April. Handbook on Communist China, circa 1968. Critical Guide to Curriculum Units and Audio-visual Materials on China, circa 1968.
- Programs, Projects and Proposals, 1966-2014; 8
  The Programs, Projects, and Proposals series in RG 7 is rather a catch-all series, as it contains both well-formed ideas files and more random project proposals. In addition to these files on possible projects, the series includes materials relating to the National Committee's early role as a Speakers Bureau. An extensive Speakers File, compiled in the late 1960s – early 1970s, contains detailed information on a wide range of China specialists who might be referred to interested organizations.
  - Program Ideas and Proposals (General), 1988-2014 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Proposed Member Trip (Lawyers) (Unrealized), 1985-1986 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    Trip proposed by Douglas Rosenthal.
  - Proposed Information Management Systems Delegation from China (Uncompleted), 1984 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    State Economic Commission delegation proposed for January-February 1985.
  - Proposed Projects - Arms Control and Disarmament (Uncompleted), 1984-1985 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    Reference file and proposed delegation from China. Original folder title, Nuclear- Strategic.
  - Proposed Projects - Han and T'ang Mural Exhibition (U.S.), 1977-1978 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Possible Projects - Photography (Uncompleted), 1979, 1982 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Proposed Projects - China Charities Foundation Study Trip (Uncompleted), 1996 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Proposed China Ethnic Minorities' Association for External Exchanges Delegation (Uncompleted), 1998, 2002, 2004 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Possible Projects - Film on China, 1970 (Box 1, Folder 9)
    Includes correspondence with Don Dixon, National Educational Television.
  - Possible Projects - Childrens Acrobatic Troupe from China, 1979 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Possible Projects - U. S. - P. R. C. Trade Negotiations Exercise and Case Studies, 1979 May 15 (Box 1, Folder 11)
    Project proposal involving New York University Graduate School of Business.
  - Possible Projects - Civil Service Delegation, 1988-1990 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Possible Projects - Military Publishers Delegations, 1989 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Possible Projects - Religion in China, 1994-1997, 2005 (Box 1, Folder 14)
    Proposals and background materials.
  - Possible Projects - Lodi Gyari Back-Channel Meeting, 1998-1999 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Possible Projects - State and City Government, 1991-1995 (Box 1, Folder 16)
    Background materials and clippings.
  - Possible Projects - Local Elections, 1996 (Box 1, Folder 17)
    Memo on Chinese electoral development and training programs run by the International Republican Institute (IRI), and possible NCUSCR cooperation.
  - Possible Projects - China Cultural Commemorative, 1996-1997 (Box 1, Folder 18)
    Outside proposal by Jack Fensterstock, China Capital Corporation, for twenty-fifth anniversary of the Shanghai Communique.
  - Comparative Crisis Project Proposal, 2001 December (Box 1, Folder 19)
    Informal proposal by Mike (David M. Lampton) for comparative study of crises in U. S. - China relations, 1989-2001.
  - Possible Projects - Legal Studies Center in Beijing (Justice Anthony M. Kennedy Proposal), 2002 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Possible Projects - Climate Change, 2007-2008 (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Project Assistance - Television Projects- Adam Smith Money World, 1993 (Box 2, Folder 22)
    Interview of Vice Premier Li Lanqing.
  - Project Assistance - New York - Beijing Sister City Committee (Lu Yucheng Visit), 1994 (Box 2, Folder 23)
    Lu Yucheng was vice mayor of Beijing. The National Committee hosted a luncheon for Lu on September 27, 1994.
  - Possible Project Partner - America Abroad Media, circa 2004 (Box 2, Folder 24)
    File included one CD (not retained) of Battling for Hearts and Minds (America Abroad radio program), ca. 2004. Broadcast program available at www.americaabroadmedia.org.
    Appraisal
  - National Committee Proposals File, 2003-2006 (Box 10, Folder 109-111)
    Chronological reference file of NCUSCR proposals submitted to U. S. government and foundation funders. Arranged in reverse chronological order.
  - National Committee Project and Proposals Budgets File, 2000s (Box 10, Folder 112)
    Reference file of Budgets submitted with NCUSCR proposals to U. S. government and foundation funders. Arranged by category. Most of the budget documents are undated.
  - Speakers' Bureau, 1966, 1969-1973 (Box 15, Folder 152-153)
  - Speakers File (A-B), late 1960s - early 1970s (Box 15, Folder 154)
    Alphabetical file of China experts, including biographical details, areas of expertise, and bibliography. A listing of experts by subject areas is found at the front of this file. File includes a portrait photograph of Claude A. Buss.